A Guide to the JMU: A Social History of Student Life Oral Histories, 1996: SdArch 7
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
JMU: A Social History of Student Life Oral Histories
1996
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Malinowski, Monica
SdArch 7
248
.32 cubic feet; 5 folders, 9 audiocassettes, 8 cds
JMU: A Social History of Student Life Oral Histories, 1996, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts and supplemental documents, conducted by a JMU student intern with four JMU alumni regarding their memories of student life at Madison College.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open to research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Monica Malinowski on May 1, 1996.
Bio/Historical Note
Monica Malinowski, a senior at James Madison University, conducted these interviews in fulfillment of a JMU student internship, during the spring of 1996.
Scope and Content
JMU: A Social History of Student Life Oral Histories, 1996, is comprised of audio recordings, transcripts and supplemental documents, conducted by a JMU student intern with four JMU alumni regarding their memories of student life at Madison College.
Arrangement
Interviews are arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Subjects:
State Normal School for Women at Harrisonburg (Harrisonburg, Va.) -- History; Madison College -- History; James Madison University -- History; James Madison University -- Students -- Social life and customs; Education, Higher -- Virginia -- Harrisonburg -- History; College students -- Manners and customs; College students -- Attitudes
Genre and Form Terms:
oral histories (literary works)
- 7-1: Background documents, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  This monograph gives a brief chronological history of JMU, first known as the State Normal [and Industrial] School for Women in Harrisonburg, Va., then as Madison College, and since 1977, as James Madison University. Mentions presidents and their contributions, with an emphasis on the social traditions and life of the institution from a student point of view. Summarizes some of the significant social history and changes which have occurred since its founding including: campus myths; freshman initiation rights; studying habits; party traditions; sports; religious activities; various codes, rules and regulations (dress, honor); the changing focus of education; political unrest; and the change from a women's institution to a co-educational one.
- 7-2: Mary Etter interviewed by Monica Malinowski, March 1, 1996
  This interview records the reflections of Mrs. Mary Spitzer Etter, (commuter student, music major, class of 1934) about college days at the Harrisonburg State Teachers College, referred to by the students during her time as Bluestone Hill (now known as James Madison University). Reminisces about Dr. P. Duke, the president; freshman class initiation (New Girl/Old Girl Wedding); various class days, May Day festivities and other social events, complete with costumes. Also, participation in academic/social groups such as the Glee club, Latin Club and other music and literary groups, Greek societies; required assemblies (story of her being mistakenly missed at assembly and the consequences), the Lyceum Programs, and special trips such as the Apple Blossom Festival in Winchester. Mentions the dedication of Wilson Hall (1931), a weekend at the college camp, and a story about Dr. Duke's and students' climb up Massanutten Peak. Talks about favorite teachers such as Miss Edna Shaeffer, her voice teacher, also mentions Dr. Wayland, the history teacher. Speaks about the college paper, the "Breeze," study habits, the library, honor code, smoking among students, and town-gown relationships. In general, creates a picture of what it was like to be a young lady at a decorous Southern women's teacher's college during Depression days. Recorded at the home of Mary S. Etter, Harrisonburg, Va. on March 1, 1996.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, March 1, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original audiocassette, March 1, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-001)
  - Original audiocassette, March 1, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-002)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-001)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-002)
  - Use copy audiocassette (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-009)
- 7-3: Caroline T. Marshall interviewed by Monica Malinowski, March 19, 1996
  This interview records the reflections of Dr. Caroline Marshall (class of 1960, dormitory student) about college days at Madison College, Harrisonburg, Va. Also records her perspective as a faculty member as well. Reminisces about the regimented dorm life (story about housemother and study/lights out policy), other rules and regulations (dress code, dating, honor code, dining etiquette); various ceremonies including May Day festivities, assemblies, class days (freshman wearing beanie hats), Saturday night movies, and Greek sororities. Mentions smoking among students; student government, town and gown relationships. Reminisces about academic life, teachers and fellow students; various campus myths (kissing rock, etc.); and the Asian flu epidemic when classes were canceled. Commented from the perspective of a faculty member about education for women, the opportunities it gave and changes that occurred as a result of co-education; also identity problem the institution has faced, in comparison to older more established schools in the state. In general, creates a picture of what it was like to be a young lady at a Southern women's liberal arts/teacher college during the 1950s. Recorded at the office of Dr. Caroline Marshall, Jackson Hall, JMU, on March 19, 1996.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, March 19, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original audiocassette, March 19, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-003)
  - Original audiocassette, March 19, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-004)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-003)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-004)
- 7-4: Lauren Webb interviewed by Monica Malinowski, March 25, 1996
  This interview records the viewpoints of Lauren Webb (class of 1996, dormitory student) about social life, etc. at James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va. during the previous four years. Mentions topics typical of a student's life during the 1990s including: athletics (ex. women's basketball) and related activities/traditions (Homecoming, singing the fight song); and the Greek influence on campus. Issues include: political issues/protests and the Student Government Association; drug use (alcohol, smoking and hard drugs); the racial climate and co-education; town and gown relationships and local volunteerism; various regulations and codes (informal dress code; honor code and concurrent lack of awareness, etc.); working students; parking problem on campus; and the advent of Internet use (e-mail) as a means of communication among students. Reflects on academic life, teachers and fellow students; also about various cultural events (Furious Flowers Conference). Briefly mentions a couple of campus myths (kissing rock, ghost in Wilson Hall, etc.). In general, reflects the viewpoints of a young woman attending JMU during the 1990s.Recorded in the dormitory room of Lauren Webb in Wampler Hall, JMU, on March 25, 1996.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, March 25, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original audiocassette, March 25, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-005)
  - Original audiocassette, March 25, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-006)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-005)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-006)
- 7-5: Robert Bernard Pritchard interviewed by Monica Malinowski, March 30, 1996
  This interview records the viewpoints of Bernie Pritchard (class of 1996, off-campus student) about social life, etc. at James Madison University, Harrisonburg, Va. during the previous four years. Mentions topics typical of a student's life during the 1990s including: athletics (ex. women's basketball; football) and related activities/traditions (Homecoming: being chose as Mr. Madison for 1995); and the Greek influence on campus. Issues include: political issues/protests and the Student Government Association (faculty/Dr. Carrier and the Physics Dept.); drug use (alcohol, smoking and hard drugs); the racial climate and co-education; town and gown relationships, living off campus and local volunteerism; various regulations and codes (informal dress code; honor code and cheating); working students; and the advent of Internet use (e-mail) as a means of communication among students. Reflects on academic life, teachers and fellow students. Briefly mentions a couple of campus myths. In general, reflects the viewpoints of a young man attending JMU during the 1990s. Recorded at the apartment of Robert Bernard "Bernie" Pritchard, Olde Mill Village, Harrisonburg, Va. on March 30, 1996.
  - Transcript and Supplemental Documents, March 30, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original audiocassette, March 30, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-007)
  - Original audiocassette, March 30, 1996 (Box 1, Audiocassette SA007-CS-008)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-007)
  - Preservation master (Box 1, Cd SA007-OP-008)